Finding Aid for Triangle Foundation Records 1987-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Triangle Foundation records 1987-2007 1990-1994
Triangle Foundation.
The Triangle Foundation is a gay and lesbian civil rights and advocacy organization, located in Detroit, Michigan and formed in 1990. Its programs include an anti-violence project, media activism, and legislative education on gay civil rights. The record group includes minutes; correspondence; press releases and publications of the Triangle Foundation; news clippings documenting issues relevant to the gay/lesbian community and of Triangle activities; and videotapes of local cable television newsmagazine Lambda Digest.
0092 Bj 2 Bj Outsize
6.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library by the Triangle Foundation on January 5, 2000. Donor no. 8920. Subsequent additions have been received.
The collection is open for research.
Triangle Foundation is a Detroit-based civil rights organization whose mission is "to promote equality and to secure freedom from violence, intimidation and discrimination for gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender persons throughout Michigan."
The Triangle Foundation began as part of the Michigan Organization for Human Rights or MOHR. The mission of this organization was to promote the education, awareness and understanding of the lives of gay men and lesbians. In 1983 the MOHR Foundation was created to receive tax deductible contributions The Lesbian Gay Foundation of Michigan was formed in 1990 when MOHR and the MOHR Foundation separated. Finally, in 1991, the Lesbian Gay Foundation of Michigan changed its name to Triangle Foundation. The pink triangle was the badge which homosexuals were required to wear in Nazi Germany and in the Nazi concentration camps. It is now an internationally recognized symbol of gay and lesbian oppression and resistance.
The new Triangle Foundation chose Jeffrey Montgomery as its President; he was later hired as executive director of the organization. Other important figures in the establishment and growth of the organization were Henry Messer and John Monahan.
The Triangle Foundation has a number of ongoing advocacy and legislative lobbying projects: Anti-Violence Project, Human Rights Project, Education, Speakers Bureau, Professional Trainings, Direct mail, Literature & publications, Legislative education/policy, Private Sector policy, Media activism, and Out-state/rural organizing.
The Triangle Foundation is a also founding member of the National Coalition of Anti-Violence Programs (NCAVP), which publishes a national survey of hate violence against GLBT people. The Foundation's major contribution to this effort is in compiling statistics from incident reports in the state of Michigan and contributing to the annual "Anti-Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Violence" report. This report provides data about the type and extent of violence that is occurring against GLBT crime victims in the United States. The Foundation also works with the GLBT community about the importance of reporting these hate crimes so that statistics can be compiled. Once an incident has been reported, the Foundation can assist the victim by acting as an advocate until the situation is resolved. In many cases, Triangle is the only source of such support.
The Human Rights Project is a referral service provided to put victims in touch with attorneys throughout Michigan who can provide needed legal advice and representation. Victims can also be referred to counselors and other support services.
The Foundation takes every opportunity to educate the public on GLBT issues. The Triangle Speakers Bureau gives presentations on topics such as civil rights, hate violence and hate crime legislation and other legal issues to many school groups, organizations and conferences. It offers training on lobbying techniques involvement in electoral politics and legislative reform, working effectively with the media, and dealing with homophobia in the workplace. Their publications and mailings also reflect these issues.
Media activism is another major function of the Triangle Foundation. Staff monitor and respond to media coverage of relevant issues and offer training to members of the media on accurate coverage of GLBT issues. Triangle provides instruction to their own leaders to effectively work with the media and alerts the media to important events and developments in the GLBT community.
A final major function of Triangle Foundation is the "Out-State" organizing. This organizing is focused on getting out into the community and establishing a positive presence at local events, beyond the urban centers in southeast Michigan. It also encourages people to be "out" (of the closet) into their own communities and active in local government and community activities.
This record group documents the administration and activities of this advocacy organization to bring public attention to issues impacting the lives of gay males and lesbians. The records include both paper and visual materials and have been divided into eight series: Audiovisual Materials, Administrative, Civil Rights, Hate Crimes, Legislative/Political, Miscellaneous, Other Organizations, Religion, and Publications and Clippings.
Subjects:
Triangle Foundation.; Gay rights--Michigan.; Gays--Michigan.; Lesbians--Michigan.; Hate crimes--Michigan.; Lesbians--Civil rights.; Lesbians--Legal status, laws, etc.--Michigan.; Religion and politics.; Violence--Michigan--Statistics.; Legislation--Michigan.; Gay liberation movement--Michigan--Detroit.; Michigan Organization for Human Rights.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Triangle Foundation.; Gay rights--Michigan.; Gay activists.; Gays--Michigan.; Lambda digest.; Lambda report.; Lambda journal.
Contributors:
Montgomery, Jeffrey.; Messer, Henry.; Archer, Dennis.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videocassettes.
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series consists of 3/4" U-matic videocassette tapes. Most of the tapes are locally produced for cable television. The Lambda Digest is a thirty-minute newsmagazine which covered items in the local and national news of interest to the gay and lesbian community. Other items in the series are interviews with members of local and national gay and lesbian organizations; as well as one tape of a public service announcement by the actress Amanda Bearse, which she made for National Coming Out Day (1994). This series covers the period 1989 to 1994, although a few tapes are undated. The tapes are in good condition. There is no indication that these tapes were produced or funded by the Triangle Foundation.
  - Lambda Digest #1 April 1990 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #2 June 1990 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #5 September 1990 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #6 October 1990 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #7 undated (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #8 February 1991 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #9 April 1991 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #10 May 1991 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #11 June 1991 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest #12 July 1991 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest [no number] October 1991 (Box 1)
  - Lambda Digest Pridefest '91 September 1991 (Box 2)
  - Lambda Journal -- Alison Bechdel Interview (Lambda Digest) March 1991 (Box 2)
  - Lambda Journal -- An Interview with George Melton (Box 2)
  - Lambda Journal -- Lesbian/Gay Pride Rally, Ann Arbor (Box 2)
  - Lambda Journal -- Special Report -- Kathleen Stoll November 1990 (Box 2)
  - National Coming Out Day -- Amanda Bearse in the Park (1994) (Box 2)
  - The Lambda Report #5 Undated (Box 2)
  - The Lambda Report #6 November 1988 (Box 2)
  - The Lambda Report #7 June 1989 (Box 2)
  - The Lambda Report #8 August 1989 (Box 2)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series consists of the internal records of the Triangle Foundation. It contains board meeting minutes, correspondence, daily logs, financial statements, and applications for grants. The activities file contains public relations statements which list the accomplishments of Triangle; the community involvement files also give an idea of how Triangle attempted to get the word out about their organization. The files on the merger and name change contain correspondence, filings with the state, and resolutions which provide background on the history of the organization. The series also contains publications and information on videos produced by Triangle. The series covers the period 1988 to 1999.
  - Activities 1993-1995, 2003 undated (Box 3)
  - Annual Dinner Addresses 2003 (Box 3)
  - Blank forms (Box 3)
  - Board meeting minutes 1991-1996 (Box 3)
  - Committees 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Community involvement
    - General 1992-1998 (Box 3)
    - Michigan State Fair 1993 (Box 3)
    - Names Project AIDS Memorial Quilt 1993 (Box 3)
    - United Way 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Youth Initiatives Project (Box 3)
  - Daily logs 1993-1995 (Box 3)
  - Financial statements 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Funding 1990-1999 (Box 3)
  - General (including bylaws, business plan and organizational chart) 1993-1998 (Box 3)
  - Media 1993-1999: communications with TV stations, etc. relating to coverage of gay/lesbian issues (Box 3)
  - Michigan Lesbian and Gay Anti-Violence Project merger 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1993-1998 (Box 3)
  - Name change from MOHR foundation to Lesbian Gay Foundation of Michigan 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Policy Profile 2003 (Box 3)
  - People and correspondence 1992-1997 (Box 3)
  - Triangle publications 1997-2000 (Box 3)
    (includes "advocacy 2000 where are we without it?")
  - Video Task Force-"Triangle Messenger" 1994 (Box 3)
- Civil Rights
  The Civil Rights series documents the activities of Triangle in its efforts to ensure equal rights for gays and lesbians. Throughout this and subsequent series there are numerous news clippings. Their presence is evidence of the media watchdog function of the Triangle Foundation. The clippings provide accounts of news stories of interest to the LGBT community, as well as documenting how the media covered topics of concern to the organization. Of particular interest in this series is the Education and Civil Rights Task Force subseries, as well as the Michigan Advisory Committee subseries. The former was a division of Triangle, formed to combat ballot initiatives in Michigan which would harm the civil rights of gays and lesbians. The Michigan Advisory Committee advised the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights on hate crimes, and Triangle testified before the committee in 1991. The subsequent report of the Committee was rejected by the U.S. Commission, and it was Triangles' belief that the rejection was due to the inclusion of a chapter on hate crimes against the gay/lesbian community. The series in general covers the period 1992-1998.
  - Education and Civil Rights Task Force
    - Background
      - Michigan anti-gay initiatives 1992-1994 (Box 3)
      - Other states' anti-gay initiatives 1992-1994 (Box 3)
    - General 1993 (Box 3)
    - Subcommittees
      - Public Information 1992-1993 (Box 3)
      - Strategic Planning 1993 (Box 3)
      - The Liberty Fund 1993 (Box 3)
  - Employment Discrimination, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Michigan Advisory Committee
    - FBI Report on Hate Crimes (Box 3)
    - Report 1992 (Box 3)
    - Report to U.S. Commission on Civil Rights (rejected) (Box 3)
  - Michigan Campaign for Human Dignity (Box 3)
  - Michigan Civil Rights Commission-Bias Crime Response Task Force (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - News clippings (civil rights, gay rights) (Box 3)
  - Wayne-Westland School Board (removal of "sexual orientation" from policies) 1997-1998 (Box 3)
- Hate Crimes
  The Hate Crimes series contains information on another aim of Triangle: to document incidents of hate crimes against GLBT persons. The files on the annual news conference (during which the annual statistics were released) and on the Community Watch Coalition (CWC) are particularly rich. The CWC is another offshoot of Triangle, which in turn had a project entitled "Copwatch," which concerns gay and police relations, and police training in understanding gay hate crimes. The case files reflect the legacy of Michigan as a sodomy and "gross indecency" state. The series covers the period 1991-1999.
  - Annual Hate Crimes News Conference/Release of Statistics 1992-1995 (Box 3)
  - Bias Crime Response Task Force Reports, 1996-1997. (Box 3)
  - Case Files 1992-1997, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Community Watch Coalition
    - Administrative 1991-1994 (Box 4)
    - Copwatch 1991-1996
      - Police brutality 1991-1999 (Box 4)
      - Police training (other organizations) 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Crime avoidance/compensation (Box 4)
  - Data collection guidelines 1991-1995 (Box 4)
  - Incident Reports
    - 1992 (Box 4)
    - 1993 (Box 4)
    - 1994 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1993-1999 (Box 4)
  - News clippings 1983-1999 (Box 4)
  - Press releases/statements/flyers 1993-1999 (Box 4)
  - Surveys 1991-1994 (Box 4)
  - "Verified Complaint for Declaratory and Injunctive Relief" court document 2001 (Box 4)
  - Vigil for GLTB victims of hate crimes (Matthew Shepard) 2002 (Box 4)
  - White House Conference on Hate Crimes (10 November 1997) (Box 4)
- Legislative/Political
  The Legislative/Political series contains materials related to another focus of Triangle: legislative education and monitoring legislation. It contains correspondence with legislators at the state and national level, including a petition to Michigan Governor John Engler to amend the Elliot-Larsen Civil Rights Act (1994). There is also information on the Ethnic Intimidation Act, the state's hate crime law, which does not mention sexual orientation. The topic of gays in the military is documented in a series of files. Much of this was sparked by the presidential campaign of then-Governor Bill Clinton. There is a file on Detroit Mayor Dennis Archer, with whom the Triangle Foundation had a good relationship (there are several 8x10 color photographs of Mayor Archer with Jeff Montgomery and John Monahan of Triangle). This series covers the period 1990-1998.
  - Correspondence 1991-1999 (Box 4)
  - Gays in the military
    - Correspondence 1991-1993 (Box 4)
    - Dean Mellbert Air Force rampage 1994 (Box 4)
    - Discrimination
      - Cases 1992-1993 (Box 4)
      - Joe Zuniga 1993 (Box 4)
      - Lansing Community College 1994 (Box 4)
      - Tim McVeigh 1998 (Box 4)
    - "Don't Ask, Don't Tell" policy/ Royal Oak Rally 1993 (Box 4)
    - Editorials 1992 (Box 4)
    - Other organizations' statements 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Newclippings 1991-1993 (Box 4)
    - Servicemembers Legal Defense Network (SLDN) (Box 4)
  - Birmingham (MI) Board of Education Election 1994 (Box 4)
  - Dennis Archer (Detroit mayor) 1994-1997 (Box 5)
  - Legislation (local, state, national) circa 1990-1997 (Box 5)
  - News clippings (gay marriage) 1992-1994 (Box 5)
  - Political
    - News clippings (politicians) 1992-1997 (Box 5)
    - Political candidates 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Presidential Debate (MSU, 19 October 1992)/Political Funeral, Washington D.C. October 1992 (Box 5)
  - Pride PAC (Triangle Foundation's legislative watchdog arm) (Box 5)
  - Vince Lombardi rest area case 1989 (Box 5)
- Other Organizations
  The Other Organizations series contains documentation of other organizations with which the Triangle Foundation either had a relationship, or on which they collected information. The organizations range from local to international, and include civil rights, censorship, women's rights, HIV-related and legal organizations. Correspondence and news clippings relating to these organizations make up the series.
  - Affirmations, Lesbian/Gay Community Center (Ferndale, MI) 1993-2001 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - ACLU (American Civil Liberties Union) 1994-1997 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - ADL (Anti-Defamation League) 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Campaign to End Homophobia 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - DAGLC (Detroit Area Gay/Lesbian Council) 1992-1993, undated (Box 5)
  - GLAAD (Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation) 1992, 1994 undated (Box 5)
  - Human Rights Campaign Fund 1990-1994 (scattered), undated (Box 5)
  - Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Lesbian and Gay Lawyers Association 1996 (Box 5)
  - Men of Color Motivational Group 1994, 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - MOSAIC (Michigan Organization for Social Advocacy and Intercultural Cooperation) 1992, 1994 (Box 5)
  - NAACP 1990s (Box 5)
  - NCAVP (National Coalition of Anti-Violence Programs)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - 1996-2002 (Box 5)
    - 1998-2002 (Box 5)
  - New York City Gay and Lesbian Anti-Violence Project 1991-1994 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - NGLTF (National Gay and Lesbian Task Force)
    - Bias crime legislation packet (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1991-1994 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - NGLTF Policy Institute
    - Anti-Gay/Lesbian Violence Report 1992 (Box 5)
    - Anti-Gay/Lesbian Violence Report 1993 (Box 5)
    - Campaign to Count and Counter Hate Crimes 1993 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - Creating Change Annual Conferences
      - Audiocassettes of 1994 Conference (Box 5)
      - Schedules and conference materials 1991-1994 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Documenting bias crimes 1990, 1992 (Box 5)
    - General 1992, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Police/Gay community relations 1986-1990 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - PFLAG (Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays) 1994 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (includes publications)
    - Censorship/Media 1993-1994 (Box 6)
    - HIV-related 1994-1995 (Box 6)
    - Local/Michigan (Box 6)
    - National (Box 6)
- Religion
  The Religion series contains materials on religious organizations that either worked with the Triangle Foundation, provided support for the gay/lesbian community, or that opposed homosexuality as a sin. The materials on the religious right range from material published by opposition groups such as People for the American Way, as well as materials produced by members of the religious right. The materials contain correspondence, news clippings, newsletters and other publications. There are two 8x10 black-and-white photographs in the file on the Bishop's Commission on AIDS. The series covers the period 1988-1999.
  - American Friends Service Committee 1991-1994 (Box 6)
  - Bishop's Commission on AIDS 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - Christ Church (Detroit MI) 1992 (Box 6)
  - Church/State separation 1988-1993 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1993-1997 (Box 6)
  - Local Gay Religious Groups 1993-1999 (Box 6)
  - News clippings/articles 1992-1999 (Box 6)
  - Religious Right
    - "The Freedom Writer" (Institute for first amendment studies) 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Family Forum 1993-1994 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous publications 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - News clippings 1990-1994 (Box 6)
    - People for the American Way 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - "Right-Wing Watch" (People for the American Way) 1992-1994 (Box 6)
  - Vatican (correspondence/news clippings) 1992-1994 (Box 6)
- Publications and Clippings
  The Publications and Clippings series is divided into two subseries. The Publications subseries contains magazines, newsletters, newspapers and reports focused on the LGBT community, and also includes materials from events such as the Reel Pride LGBT Film Fest and the Motor City Pride festival. Publications by Triangle can be found in the Administrative series. The Clippings subseries contains articles from publications such as Between the Lines and local news sources. These articles document events and policies related to the LGBT community and Triangle. Publications and clippings by topic are scattered throughout the collection.
  - Publications
    - 1998 Hate Crime Laws (a publication of the Anti-Defamation League), 1997 (Box 6)
    - "Anti-Lesbian, Gay, Transgender and Bisexual Violence in 2000" (National Coalition of Anti-Violence Programs report) 2001 (Box 6)
    - Between the Lines 1996-2006 (Box 6)
    - Black and White Men Together (BWMT)-Detroit 1997 (Box 6)
    - Cinevista News 1996 (Box 6)
    - Cruise and Metra ("bar rags") (Box 6)
    - Downriver Pride 1999 (Box 6)
    - Gerbil: A Queer Culture Zine undated (Box 6)
    - LGBT News by the Lansing Association for Human Rights 1997, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Motor City Business Forum,1990s (Box 6)
    - Motor City Pride 2003-2005 (Box 6)
    - Networking 45º North 1998 (Box 6)
    - Out & Voting: The Gay, Lesbian and Bisexual Vote in Congressional House Election 1998, 2000 (Box 6)
    - Outpost (Box 6)
    - Reel Pride Michigan GLBT Film Festival 2003-2006 (Box 6)
    - "Same-sex Couples and the Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual Population: New Estimates from the American Community Survey," 2006 (Box 6)
    - Second Stone: The National Newspaper for Gay and Lesbian Christians 1991 (Box 6)
    - The Network News by the Lesbian & Gay Community Network of Western Michigan, Inc. 1994, 1999 (Box 6)
    - The Third Coast 1997-1998 (Box 6)
    - Victory! America's Gay & Lesbian Business 1995 (Box 6)
    - Wrap-Up 1998 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Michigan (Box 6)
      - Out of state (Box 6)
  - Clippings
    - Anti-homophobia 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - Events 1999-2006, 8 folders (Box 6)
    - Policy 1999-2000, 2002-2006, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Policy and events 2003 (Box 7)
    - Victims 2003, 2005 (Box 7)
    - Victims advocacy 1999-2002 (Box 7)
    - Youth 2003 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1992-1999 (Box 7)
      - 1996-2007 (scattered), undated (Box 7)
      - 2006 (Box 7)